PORFIRIO BASALDUA

SOFTWARE ENGINEER

https://mxporf.github.io/

PROFILE

An experienced software engineer with more than 6 years serving in development and leadership roles, worked on distributed, scalable and resilient cloud-native systems. Looking to apply this expertise to the field of Machine Learning, take on new challenges and make meaningful contributions as part of a crossfunctional team.

CONTACT INFORMATION

Phone: (+52) 55 65 08 37 22 Email: porfirioBasaldua@gmail.com LinkedIn: linkedin.com/in/basporfirio https://mxporf.github.io/portfolio.html

CERTIFICATIONS

April 2023. AWS Machine Learning Engineer Udacity.

December 2021. Professional Cloud Architect - Google Cloud Platform.

SKILLS

Soft skills

- Active listening.
- Effective communication.
- Leadership.
- · Coaching.
- Teamwork.
- Problem solving.
- Critical thinking.

Programming and tools

- Python (Advanced).
- SQL (Advanced).
- Sci-kit learn (Advanced).
- Pandas (Advanced).
- PyTorch (Intermediate).
- Numpy (Intermediate).
- AWS Sagemaker (Intermediate).
- AWS Lambda (Intermediate).
- AWS S3 (Intermediate).
- AWS EC2 (Intermediate).

Languages

- English (Advanced).
- Spanish (Native).

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Lead Software Engineer

 $IBM \ (consultant \ through \ Persistent \ Systems)$

December 2022 - Present

- Collaborated on the development and implementation of a Machine Learning system on the cloud to estimate the probability of survival for oncology patients.
- Played a key role in the development, testing, and maintenance of public APIs for the IBM cloud platform. Designed and implemented robust and scalable APIs, adhering to industry best practices and standards.
- Worked closely with product managers and external partners to gather requirements and deliver seamless integration capabilities.
- Designed and implemented robust pipelines to automate testing and deployment processes, leveraging Infrastructure as Code principles.
- Automated the creation and execution of comprehensive test suites, ensuring highquality software releases.
- Actively engaged in agile development methodologies to prioritize tasks, allocate resources effectively, and deliver software solutions within tight deadlines.
- Demonstrated strong problem-solving skills and adaptability in a fast-paced and dynamic work environment.

Technical Lead

Vexi

January 2021 - December 2022

- Developed custom reports and dashboards to track finance-related KPIs, leveraging individual and aggregate data to provide valuable insights to the collections department.
- Designed a database structure that aided the accounting department to operate reliably and with accourate, up-to-date information.
- Redesigned monolithic applications into microservices and APIs, enhancing scalability and maintainability.
- Successfully migrated workloads to a cloud environment in AWS, optimizing resource utilization and ensuring high availability.
- Acted as a point of contact for external stakeholders and team leaders, fostering cooperation and coordinating dependencies.
- Mentored junior developers, assisting them in overcoming technical challenges and fostering their professional growth.

Full Stack Developer

Vexi

February 2018 - December 2020

- Designed and implemented automatic testing and deployment pipelines for seamless integration and delivery of software.
- Created pipelines to gather and process client information in real time, enabling timely and accurate data analysis.
- Utilized external APIs to enhance processes within the customer satisfaction department, leveraging third-party tools.
- Collaborated with stakeholders to implement SQL queries and reports, enabling business managers to monitor key metrics for their processes.

EDUCATION

Monterrey Institute of Technology and Higher Education

Bachelor of Science in Robotics and Digital Systems, August 2012 - December 2016

- Graduated with honors.
- Score of 90 / 100.
- Volunteer for student association.